A Guide to the James Whitcomb Riley Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7133-q
James Whitcomb Riley Collection 1867-1940
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7133-q
ca. 700 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1972 September 8
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, "At Laker-Bee", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "The Curse of the Wandering Foot", AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "An Empty Glove", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "John Brown", n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "An Order for a Song", n.d.; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, "Song", n.d.; AMss, 1 p.
  - List of poems on back of envelope, [ca. 1891 Feb]; AMs
  - Poems and drawings written and drawn by James Whitcomb Riley as a child, Photostats, 17 items
  - Poem, "The Bear Story", n.d.; 2 photostats of AMs (incom.), 2 p. each
  - Poem, "The Raggedy Man Observing", n.d.; Typed trans., 1 p.
  - Poem, "Bud Writes Some Rhymes", n.d.; Typed trans., 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Letter To a Child's Mother", n.d.; Typed trans., 1 p.
  - Poem, "A Sonnet", n.d.; Typed trans., 1 p.
- Letters
  - Viola Allen to James Whitcomb Riley, 1916 Jan 31; ALS, 4 p. w/env
  - Frances Hodgson Burnett to James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Nov 26; ALS, 4 p.
  - R. L. Dawson to James Whitcomb Riley, 1890 Nov 11; ALS, 1 p.
  - Margaret Deland to James Whitcomb Riley, 1916 Mar 27; TLS, 1 p.
  - Julian Riley Dillaby to James Whitcomb Riley, 1897 Apr 30; ALS, 3 p. w/env
  - Mary Dodds to James Whitcomb Riley, 1896 Nov 9; ALS, 6 p. w/env
  - Ed[mund Eitel] to James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Mar 1; TLS, 2 p. w/env
  - Carl Fisher to Guards of Indianapolis Speedway, re: James Whitcomb Riley, 1916 May 24; TLS, 1 p.
  - Libbie Fisher to James Whitcomb Riley, 1892 Jun 2; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - Hotel Halcyon to James Whitcomb Riley, 1915; 4 bills
  - K. O. Hert to A. J. Walker re: James Whitcomb Riley's talk, 1888 Jul 4; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - O[liver] W[endell] Holmes to [ James Whitcomb Riley?], 1867 Dec 28; ALS, 4 p.
  - W[illiam] D[ean] Howells to James Whitcomb Riley, 1916 Feb 22; ALS, 2 p.
  - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, 1903 May 15; LS, 2 p. w/env
  - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, encl. 2 1. AMs poem by Mitchell, [1903 Aug 18]; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, 1904 Dec 12; TLS, 3 p. w/env
  - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, [1906 Jan 10]; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - Letters, [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, 1903-1913; TMs (trans.), 3 p.
  - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to James Whitcomb Riley, 1906 May 27; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - Frank Moore to James Whitcomb Riley, encl. 19 1. AMs essay, "An American Poet" by Mira Southworth, 1901 Jul 17; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - Munford to James Whitcomb Riley, 1899 Mar 11; ALS, 3 p.
  - F[rank] Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; ALS, 3 p.
  - George Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, 1884 Jun 21; ALS, 2 p. w/env
  - Lesley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, encl. clippings, 1907 Jul 17; ALS, 10 p. w/env
  - Lesley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, 1907 Aug 20; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - Lesley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, encl. clipping, 1907 Aug 21; ALS, 8 p. w/env
  - Lesley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, encl. clippings and 2 photos, 1908 Feb 13; ALS, 12 p.
  - Mary Riley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, 1889 Aug 27; ALS, 3 p.
  - Mary Riley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, [1889] Sep 7; ALS, 4 p. w/env
  - Mary Riley Payne to James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; ALS, 4 p.
  - Gene Stratton Porter to James Whitcomb Riley, [1910 Jan 5]; ALS, 3 p. w/env
  - Julia Riley to [ James Whitcomb Riley], n.d.; ALS (incom.), 4 p.
  - Inscribed to James Whitcomb Riley by Molly Elliott Seawell, [1915 Dec 23]; Inscribed calling card w/env
  - John Philip Sousa to James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Dec 15; ALS, 1 p. w/env
  - Ella [Wheeler Wilcox] to James Whitcomb Riley, 1876 Nov 7; ALS, 14 p.
  - William Winter to James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Oct 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - Unknown to James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; AN in form of poem, 1 p.
  - James Whitcomb Riley to Unknown, 1877 Jan 11; ALS (trans.) in form of poem, 5 p.
  - Letters from James Whitcomb Riley to Henderson and others, 1877; TMs (trans.), 3 p.
- Miscellaneous
  - Agreement between James Whitcomb Riley and Minneapolis Institute of Arts and Letters, re: James Whitcomb Riley's speeches, 1899 Aug 31; Legal document
  - Page proofs for several poems by James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; Page proofs, w/AMs corr., 8 items
  - Re: James Whitcomb Riley's works, Riley Hospital, Riley Memorial, etc., ca. 1905-ca. 1935; Clippings, ca. 300 items
  - Poems of James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; Clippings, 17 items
- Papers of Mary and Lesley Payne
  - Business Papers
    Note: As much as possible, the list follows Lesley Payne's filing order and folder headings.
    - From Library of Congress Copyright Office for James Whitcomb Riley works, w/envelope, 1901-1931; 17 cards and letters, w/env
    - Duplicates of papers submitted to James Noel re: motion picture rights, Bobbs-Merrill subscription edition, 1912-1922; Correspondence and memoranda
    - Between Lesley Payne and book companies, re: proposal to publish James Whitcomb Riley letters, 1912-1923; Correspondence and agreements
    - Corr. between Riley heirs; history of James Whitcomb Riley estate; list of James Whitcomb Riley property in hands of Edmund Eitel, 1913-1919; Correspondence and memoranda
    - Re: James Whitcomb Riley estate; copyrights, etc., 1914-1923; Correspondence, agreements, memoranda
    - Re: Scribner's Homestead Edition and relinquishment to Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1915-1917; Correspondence and agreements
    - Bobbs-Merrill Co. to Marcus Dickey, re: proposed book on James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Mar 16; Trans. of TLS
    - Will for Mary Riley Payne, 1917 Oct 11; Will
    - Includes statements of George Ray and Mary Judah, 1917; Notes and statements
    - Re: James Whitcomb Riley Memorial; distribution of shares in estate, 1917-1919; Agreements
    - Re: Bottsford letters, Riley baby pictures, 1917-1919; Correspondence
    - Frederic Burlingame to Lesley Payne, re: literary and movie rights, 1917-1921; 3 TLS
    - Re: James Whitcomb Riley estate and movie rights, 1917-1923; Correspondence, affidavits, memoranda
    - Re: subscription edition, serial articles, royalties, 1917-1923; Correspondence and contracts
    - Between James Whitcomb Riley heirs and Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1918-1919; Drafts of contracts
    - Re: settlement of James Whitcomb Riley estate, 1918-1927; Correspondence and agreements
    - Agreement between Mary Riley Payne and J. M. Judah, 1919 Nov 3; Deposit agreement
    - Charles Miller to Lesley Payne, re: taxes, James Whitcomb Riley memorial, 1920; 19 TLS
    - Charles Miller to Lesley Payne, re: royalties, taxes, 1921; 20 TLS
    - Chiefly from Ernest Bradford and William Osborne, re: James Whitcomb Riley copyrights, 1922-1927; Copies of correspondence and memoranda
    - Re: settlement of James Whitcomb Riley estate, 1922-1928; Correspondence, memoranda, contracts
    - Re: James Whitcomb Riley copyrights, 1925-1927; Correspondence
    - Re: rights of "Little Orphant Annie", 1926; Correspondence
    - Representative of Mary Riley Payne to Albert Beveridge, re: edition of James Whitcomb Riley letters, 1926; 2 TL
    - Correspondence between James Whitcomb Riley heirs; contracts with Bobbs-Merrill Co., re: rights to Ripley material, 1926-1929; Correspondence and contracts
    - Mary Stubbs to Lesley Payne, re: income, 1927 Dec 19; TLS
    - Re: permissions to use James Whitcomb Riley poems, 1928; Correspondence
    - Re: James Whitcomb Riley copyrights, 1928-1929; Correspondence
    - From Victor Talking Machine Co., 1928-1930; Correspondence and royalty statements
    - Browne and Phelps to Bobbs-Merrill Co., re: copyrights for James Whitcomb Riley heirs, 1934-1936; 2 TL
    - Re: Mary Riley Payne's estate, 1938 Jan 25; Correspondence and inventory
    - To Riley heirs for The Bachelor Bard, 1938 Sep 23; Assignment of copyright
    - Elizabeth and Harry Miesse to Lesley Payne, re: finances, 1939-1943; 10 ALS/TLS
    - Between James Whitcomb Riley and Bobbs-Merrill, Memorandum of contract
    - Re: rights to James Whitcomb Riley letters, n.d.; Memorandum
    - Inventories of James Whitcomb Riley letters, manuscripts, and records, Typed inventories
  - Personal Papers
    - Diary of Lesley Payne, 1906; AMsS, ca. 40 p.
    - Lesley Payne's list of James Whitcomb Riley letters, in notebook, n.d.; AMs, ca. 75 p.
    - "James Whitcomb Riley" by Lesley Payne, n.d.; TMs (carbon, incom.), 60 p.
    - Lesley Payne's notes for biography of James Whitcomb Riley, n.d.; AMs, ca. 35 p.
    - Genealogical notes re: Riley family, n.d.; TMs, 2 p.
    - Speech, "Memories of Riley" by William Hough, n.d.; TMs, 11 p.
    - Poem beginning, "Down the lane he comes..." by unknown, n.d.; AMs, 2 p.
    - Metaphysical notes by [ Mary Riley Payne], n.d.; AMs and TMs, ca. 50 p.
  - Letters
    - J. H. Armington to Lesley Payne, 1939 Mar 31; TLS, 1 p.
    - Jessie [Barroquillo] to Lesley Payne, 1940 Mar 28; ALS, 2 p.
    - Clara [Bottsford] to Mary Riley Payne, 1887 Sep 7; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1911 Oct 9; ALS, 3 p.
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, [1912] Feb 26; ALS, 8 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1912 Mar 26; ALS, 8 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, [1912] May 6; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1912 Sep 5; ALS, 4 p.
    - Guido Della Bona to [ Lesley Payne], 1912 Sep 21; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1912 Nov 2; ALS, 4 p.
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1913 [Aug 22]; ALS, 2 p.
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, encl. photo, 1914 May 21; ALS, 4 p.
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, 1914 Jan 8; ALS, 4 p. w/env
    - Guido Della Bona to Lesley Payne, Sep 4; ALS, 4 p.
    - Marcus Dickey to Lesley Payne, 1935 May 1; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    - Arthur Downing to Lesley Payne, 1939 Apr 25; TLS, 3 p.
    - David Francis to Henry Eitel, 1916 Aug 31; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    - Citizens of Greenfield to Mary Riley Payne, bound, [1916]; TLS, 8 p.
    - George Hitt to Arthur Swann, 1935 Mar 16; TLS (carbon), 2 p. w/env
    - George Hitt to Lesley Payne, 1936 Aug 3; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    - H. K. Landis to Lesley Payne, 1939 Mar 22; ALS, 1 p.
    - M. McKenzie to Mary Riley Payne, 1892 Jul 26; ALS, 2 p.
    - Albert Macy to Lesley Payne, encl. photo of Macy, 1938 Jan 17; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    - [Silas] Weir Mitchell to Edmund Eitel, 1913 Feb 3; TLS, 1 p.
    - Lesley Payne to unknown, n.d.; AL (draft), 1 p.
    - Mary Riley Payne to Dr. Murphy, n.d.; ALS, 4 p.
    - Julia Riley to Mary Riley Payne, 1927 Oct 24; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    - Richard Riley to Mary Riley Payne, 1929 Mar 8; TLS, 1 p.
    - Mary Roberts Rinehart to [Edmund] Eitel, 1917 Feb 22; TLS, 1 p.
    - John Townsend Trowbridge to [Edmund] Eitel, 1915 Jun 29; ALS, 4 p.
    - Clara Wambach to Mary Riley Payne, 1903 Sep 23; ALS, 11 p. w/env
- Photographs
  - James Whitcomb Riley, head and shoulders, 1892 Oct; 6 copies of photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, standing, Photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, seated, w/unidentified man standing beside him, 2 copies of photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, seated, n.d.; Photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, profile, n.d.; Photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, head and shoulders, Photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, standing, 2 copies of photo
  - James Whitcomb Riley, head and shoulders, Photo from book
  - James Whitcomb Riley, half-seated on chair, n.d.; 3 photos on posters
  - James Whitcomb Riley, w/members of the Payne family, n.d.; Photo
  - Riley monument in Indianapolis, Photo on card
  - Riley hospital in Indianapolis, Photo on card
  - "The Old Swimming Hole" in Greenfield, Indiana, Photo on card
  - Old Seminary Homestead in Greenfield, Indiana, Photo on card
  - Lesley Payne as a child, n.d.; 3 photos
  - Lesley Payne, older, standing, Photo
  - Lesley Payne, profile, n.d.; Photo
  - Lesley Payne, seated, n.d.; Photo
  - Four unidentified men, n.d.; 2 tintypes
  - Unidentified man, head and shoulders, Photo
  - Unidentified man with beard, seated, n.d.; Photo
  - [For photos of Mary Riley Payne and Lesley Payne], 4 negatives
  - Hall Caine, seated, n.d.; Photo
  - Clara Laughlin, profile, n.d.; Photo, signed
- Miscellaneous
  - Notes, envelopes, cards, etc., 1886-1930, n.d.; Miscellaneous items